Tengxiang Zhang

I am an Assistant Research Scientist at Pervasive Computing Research Center, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. I build pervasive interfaces to bridge the digital and physical world. My research interests include: 1) Sustainable sensing and interactive systems; 2) Thing-computer interconnection techniques; 3) Human-AI interaction and collaboration.

EDUCATION

2016-2019	PhD, Human Computer Interaction, Computer Science	
	Tsinghua University, China	Advisor: Prof. Yuanchun Shi
2011-2013	MSc, Electromagnetics, Electrical Engineering	
	The University of Texas at Austin, USA	Advisor: Prof. Andrea Alu
2007-2011	BSc, Chien-Shiung Wu Honors College/Electrical Engineering	
	Southeast University, China	Prof. Tiejun Cui's Lab

PUBLICATIONS

- **2020** [J.8] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Steve Hodges, Yiqiang Chen. Backscatter Sensing: An Emerging Solution for Data Collection and Interaction at The Very Edge of The Network. Submitted to IEEE Pervasive Computing. (*under review*)
 - [C.4] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Jiang, Yinshuai Zhang, Xuhai Xu, Xin Zeng, Jennifer Mankoff, Anind Dey, Yiqiang Chen. BoldMove: Leveraging Semantics to Facilitate Gestural IoT Device Control. Submitted to ACM CHI'21. (under review)
 - [J.7] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Zi Qian, HsuanWei Fan, Jie Ren, Yuntao Wang, Yuanchun Shi. Easily-add Battery-free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects: A System Implementation and Evaluation of BitID. Submitted to Elsevier Pervasive and Mobile Computing. (under review)
 - [J.6] Yingwei Zhang, Yiqiang Chen, Hanchao Yu, Zeping Lv, Xiaodong Yang, Chunyu Hu, **Tengxiang Zhang**. What Can "Drag & Drop" Tell? Detecting Mild Cognitive Impairment by Hand Motor Function Assessment under Dual-Task Paradigm. *International Journal of Human-Computer Studies 145:102547*.
 - [C.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yinshuai Zhang, Ke Sun, Yuntao Wang, and Yiqiang Chen. 2020. ThermalRing: Gesture and Tag Inputs Enabled by a Thermal Imaging Smart Ring. *In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*, 1–13.
 - [C.2] Yuntao Wang, Zichao (Tyson) Chen, Hanchuan Li, Zhengyi Cao, Huiyi Luo, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Ke Ou, John Raiti, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. 2020. MoveVR: Enabling Multiform Force Feedback in Virtual Reality using Household Cleaning Robot. *In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*, 1–12.
 - [O.4] **Tengxiang Zhang** and Steve Hodges. New Opportunities for Sustainable Interaction using Backscatter Sensors. *Workshop on self-powered sustainable interfaces and interactions (SelfSustainableCHI 2020)*

- **2019** [J.5] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Jiayuan Gao, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Simin Li, Yuanchun Shi. Facilitating Temporal Synchronous Target Selection through User Behavior Modeling. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 2,4:159.
 - [J.4] Yuntao Wang, Jianyu Zhou, Hanchuan Li, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Minxuan Gao, Zhuolin Cheng, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. FlexTouch: Enabling Large-Scale Interaction Sensing Beyond Touchscreens Using Flexible and Conductive Materials. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 3,3:109.
 - [O.3] Jianfei Shen, **Tengxiang Zhang**, and Yiqiang Chen. Tap2Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Tapping. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '19*, *Pages 346-349*.
- **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Yiqin Lu, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. Tap-to-Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Synchronous Tapping. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 2, 4: 201.
 - [O.2] **Tengxiang Zhang**. 2018. Toward Pervasive Interaction: Empowering and Enriching Interactions on Resource-constrained Devices. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '18*, Pages 504-509.
 - [O.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. TOUCHPOWER: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *GetMobile: Mobile Comp. and Comm.* 22, 2: 27–31. (*Invited Highlights*)
- **2017** [J.2] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. TouchPower: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 1, 3: 121:1–121:20. (*Discussion Paper*)
 - [C.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Nicholas Becker, Yuntao Wang, Yuan Zhou, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. BitID: Easily Add Battery-Free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects. *In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing (SMARTCOMP)*, 1–8. (Best Paper Runner-up)
- 2013 [J.1] Huifeng Ma, Bengeng Cai, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Yan Yang, Weixiang Jiang, and Tiejun Cui. 2013. Three-Dimensional Gradient-Index Materials and Their Applications in Microwave Lens Antennas. *IEEE Transactions on Antennas and Propagation* 61, 5: 2561–2569.

PATENTS

- **2020** [P.9] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Smart Ring Based Input Method, System, and Apparatus: CN 202010413596.3 (*pending*)
 - [P.8] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Smart Ring Based Gesture Recognition Method and System: CN 202010411317.X (*pending*)
 - [P.7] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. Apparatus and Method for Cognitive Load Analysis Based on Near-infrared Imaging of Subcutaneous Veins: CN 202010459503.0 (pending)

- [P.6] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. A Movement Symmetry Based Smart Prosthesis Control Method and System: CN 202010425034.0 (*pending*)
- **2018** [P.5] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang**. Smart Ring and its Wearing Method: CN 201810971684.8 (*pending*)
 - [P.4] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang**. One type of Smart Ring: CN 201821371671.9
 - [P.3] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang.** Smart Ring: CN 201821371641.8
 - [P.2] Yuanchun Shi, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang and Chun Yu. Pairing method and wireless device for pairing using wireless signals. International Patent No. PCT/CN2018/094468.
 - [P.1] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu. An association method and apparatus to pair devices based on wireless signals: CN 201810723952.4

GRANTS

- **2020** [I.2] **Principle Investigator:** Resources Cross-modality Association and Matching Techniques (1.08 Million CNY), sub-project of Key Technologies for Modern Service Resource Management, National Key Research and Development Plan.
 - [I.1] **Co-investigator:** Hearing Aid Automatic Fitting Models (0.3 Million CNY), Key Technologies of Proactive Health and Aging Population, National Key Research and Development Plan.

HONORS AND AWARDS

2019	Graduate with Honor (CS), Tsinghua University, China	
2018	Finalist, Global Innovation Competition'18	
2017	Best Paper Runner-up, SMARTCOMP'17	
2017	Discussion Paper, UbiComp'17	
2012	First Prize, International Mathematical Contest in Modeling	

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2019-present Assistant Research Scientist, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

- Conduct research on ultra-low-power sensors, wearable devices, and humancentered interconnections techniques
- Ubiquitous sensing hardware: Analog backscatter wireless touch sensing interface with μW power consumption (on-going)
- User-centered collaborative system: AR-facilitated digital resource manipulation (on-going)
- Pervasive interaction technique: Function association mechanism for gesture interfaces (*on-going*)

2015-2016 RF Engineer/Product Manager, Tomoon Technology, Beijing, China

• Smartwatch and Bluetooth tracker antenna design

• Bluetooth tracker product definition, project management, field deployment

2013-2015 Product and Test Engineer, Silicon Labs, Austin, Texas, USA

• IoT MCU chips (e.g. Sub-GHz, ZigBee) RF calibration and test

• Test program (C/Perl) development, hardware design and layout

Developed on-chip test program that saved over 30% test time for EM357

SERVICES

Review CHI'20'21, IMWUT'20, UIST'20, MobileHCI'20, ISS'20, IUI'20,

TEI'20, EICS'19, TEI'21 WIP Program Committee

Volunteer ACM UBICOMP/ISWC 2018, Singapore;

The 4th UN World Urban Forum 2008, Nanjing, China

Academic Speaker GIX 2020 Access Computing Summer Program

Mentor GIX 2019 Winter Camp

STUDENT SUPERVISION AND MENTORSHIP

Xin Zeng UCAS Ph.D (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang Chen

Xinyi YangBJTU Undergraduate (CS)Xinran ChenUESTC Undergraduate (CS)

Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Ph.D at UCAS (CS)

*Jiayin Wang

*Simin Li

Beihang Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Tsinghua (CS)

*Zi Qian

Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Georgia Tech (CS)

*Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at U of Toronto (CS)

*Hsuan-Wei Fan

Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Cornell Tech (CS)

*Hanwei Wang

Tsinghua Undergraduate (Physics); Now Ph.D at UIUC (EE)

* Alumni

SKILLS

Programming languages: Python, C, C++, C#, Java, Matlab

Prototyping: Arduino, Processing, Altium, 3D printing

Software: Matlab, CST, Keras, Scikit-learn

Hardware: Signal generator, Vector network analyzer, Spectrum analyzer